Finding aid for Myron E. Wegman Papers, 1939-2004
Bentley Historical Library
Myron E. Wegman Papers
1939-2004
1960-1988
Bentley Historical Library
Wegman, Myron E.
89211 Aa 2
11 linear feet
Myron Ezra Wegman, 1908-2004, was a leader in public health and clinical pediatrics for seven decades. The collection consists of personal and professional papers covering his career in medicine and public health and includes correspondence, reports, speeches, travel diaries, course material, reprints, and minutes and notes on organizations to which he belonged.
The collection was the gift of Professor Myron Wegman (donor no. 7585 ). The papers were received in multiple accessions: 1988, 1997, and 2004.
The collection is open to research.
Myron Wegman, Dean of the University of Michigan School of Public Health from 1960 to 1974 and Professor of Pediatrics and Communicable Diseases in the Medical School was born on July 23, 1908 in Brooklyn, New York. He was educated at the City College of New York (BA 1928), Yale University (MD 1932), and Johns Hopkins University (MPH, 1938).
His career began in 1936 with the Maryland State Health Department, Bureau of Child Hygiene. He spent a year, 1941-1942, at the School of Tropical Health in San Juan, Puerto Rico and then worked at the New York City Health Department while teaching part time at Johns Hopkins University, Columbia, and Cornell. In 1946 he took the position of professor and head of Pediatrics for Louisiana State University Medical School. From 1952 to 1960, Wegman held several positions in the World Health Organization (WHO), including chief of education and training, secretary-general, and consultant to the Pan American Health Organization (PAHO).
When Wegman became Dean of the University of Michigan School of Public Health in 1960, he was a well-established figure in the field of public health and a respected specialist in child health care. Wegman's work reflects a concern for the best possible health care for the greatest number of people, a position which was cause for worry for many administrators and medical care professionals because it implied a substantial financial commitment and institutional restructuring. While at the University of Michigan, Wegman served on the Commission on the Reduction of Excess Hospital Capacity. Here he was given the difficult task of targeting hospitals for bed reduction. Dr. Wegman also headed the push to implement HMOs at the university, a proposal vigorously resisted by administrators.
Dr. Wegman served on numerous committees and boards, often assisting with project implementation. He was one of the developers of Project HEADSTART. He helped to develop three health planning organizations; he was President of the Comprehensive Health Planning Council of Southeastern Michigan and member of the Michigan State Public Health Advisory Council. He was active in the American Academy of Pediatrics, the American Board of Preventative Medicine, and the American Medical Association among other health organizations. His annual reports on world infant mortality in the journal Pediatrics from 1950 to 1997, gave him international repute as an authority on child health.
Among the many honors he received during his career were: the Sedgwick Medal, the highest award of the American Public Health Association, Man of the Year from the City College of New York, the Clifford G. Grulee Medal from the American Academy of Pediatrics, the Bronfman Prize from the American Public Health Association. On his eightieth birthday, the Myron E. Wegman Endowed Scholarship Fund was begun in tribute to his many professional accomplishments.
In retirement with emeritus status, Wegman pursued many professional activities as a consultant, public speaker, and advisor. In 1990 he was coordinator for the university's collaboration with the Autonomous University of Madrid. He died April 12, 2004.
The Myron Ezra Wegman collection is divided into seven series: Biographical and Early Materials, 1939-2004, University of Michigan, 1960-1988, Comprehensive Health Planning Organizations, 1968-1979, Associations, Committees, and Projects, 1949-1990, Post-Retirement Period, 1974-1993, Reprints, 1930-1989, and Topical Files.
Health maintenance organizations.; Medical care.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Commission on Reduction of Excess Hospital Capacity in Southeastern Michigan.; Community Health Incorporated.; Comprehensive Health Planning Council of Southeastern Michigan.; Michigan. Governor's Action Committee on Health Care.; Pan American Health Organization.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; Wegman, Myron E.; World Health Organization.; Wegman, Myron E.
- Biographical and Early Materials, 1939-2004
  Biographical and Early Materials, 1939-2004 contains correspondence, reports, and teaching materials evidence of Wegman's career before joining the faculty of the University of Michigan. Of particular note are the materials from a 1949 protest against the medical profession, which resulted in Wegman's dismissal from a lecturing appointment in Arkansas. The incident gained national attention. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Biographical, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Early Correspondence
    - Personal Correspondence, 1942-1959 (Box 1)
    - Professional Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 1)
    - "Protest Against Present Attitudes." and Arkansas School of Medicine, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Playtex Park Research Institute, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1939-1995 (Box 1)
  - Reports and Lectures, 1942-1947 (Box 1)
  - Teaching Materials, 1939-1946; 2 folders (Box 1)
    (Johns Hopkins University, Maryland State Health Department, School of Tropical Health, Louisiana State University)
  - WHO Study, Infant Diarrhea in Fin, 1950 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan, 1959-1990
  The University of Michigan, 1960-1988 series is comprised of committee files, course materials for the School of Public Health, correspondence and memoranda reflecting some educational and administrative concerns. Here there is Wegman's' study of a possible Health Maintenance Organization for the University, which is an early version of the HMO subsequently adopted. The series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Medical School Committees
    - Committee to Assess Periodic Health Appraisal Unit (PHAU), 1975-1983 (Box 1)
    - Nursing Ph.D. Review Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Health and Disease Committee, PH 650, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1983; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Course Materials, 1962-1990
    - Clinical Medicine 500 (Box 1)
    - International Health 514 (Box 1)
    - Health and Disease 650 (Box 1)
    - Disease Process Seminar, 651 (Box 1)
    - International Health 660 (Box 1)
    - Lecture Notes, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Development (Box 2)
  - Dean Selection Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Department of Health Planning and Administration
    - Correspondence, 1975-1979; 1982 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Meetings, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
  - General Administrative Communications, 1964-1990 (Box 2)
  - Health Maintenance Organization (HMO) study for University of Michigan
    - Background and Reports, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Documents, 1979 (Box 2)
    - "Health Maintenance Organization for Washtenaw County", 1975 (Box 2)
    - Final Reports, 1980 (Box 2)
- Comprehensive Health Planning Organizations, 1968-1980
  The third series is Comprehensive Health Planning Organizations, 1968-1979. Through minutes, memoranda, reports, and correspondence, this group documents the development, activities, concerns, and recommendations of three health planning organizations with which Wegman was intimately involved.: the Areawide Health Operating Committee, 1969-1970, the Comprehensive Health Planning Council of Southeastern Michigan, 1971-1979, and Community Health Incorporated, 1968-1973. These organizations made recommendations regarding proposed health facilities and worked with existing community health organizations, helping them to respond productively to health care needs.
  - Areawide Health Operating Committee, 1969-1970
    - Communications, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Minutes, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Transcripts of meetings, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Transition to Comprehensive Health Planning Council (Box 2)
  - Comprehensive Health Planning Council, 1971-1980
    - Administration, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Communication, Memoranda
      - 1970 (Box 3)
      - 1971, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1972, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - 1973, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - 1974, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1978-1980 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1973; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Grant Application, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Minutes, Executive Committee, 1970-1971; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Planning Committees
      - Environmental Health (Box 4)
      - Health Facilities (Box 4)
      - Health Personnel (Box 4)
      - Mental Health (Box 4)
    - Program of Work, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
    - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital relocation, 1973; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Washtenaw County Group, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Greater Detroit Area Hospital Council, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Community Health Incorporated, 1968-1973; 7 folders (Box 5)
- Associations, Committees, and Projects, 1949-1991
  Associations, Committees, and Projects, 1949-1990 is a large series comprised of correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, and some reference materials. Among the groups documented here are the unpopular Commissions of Reduction of Excess Hospital Capacity, 1977-1980, the Governor's Action Committee on Health Care, 1964-1966, Project HEADSTART, and several seminars. The "Seminar on the Rational Uses of Medicine, 1974-1978, was concerned with supporting legislation regarding adequate drug labeling on medicines in other countries and responsible advertising. A large part of this series is devoted to Wegman's activities in WHO, 1950-1991, including travel diaries which are descriptive narratives on his many foreign assignments with WHO, as well as other trips abroad. This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American Academy of Pediatrics
    - Committee on International Child Health, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1986 (Box 5)
    - Editorial Board of Pediatrics, 1949-1990; 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Michigan Chapter, 1978 (Box 5)
  - American Association for World Health, 1982-1986 (Box 5)
  - American Board of Pediatrics, 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - American Board of Preventative Medicine, 1959-1974 (Box 5)
  - American Journal of Public Health, Editorial Board, 1979-1989 (Box 5)
  - American Medical Association, 1961-1968; 1972 (Box 5)
  - American Pediatric Society, 1958-1968; 1975-1987 (Box 5)
  - American Public Health Association, 1971; 1974-1989 (Box 5)
  - Association of Medical Colleges, 1961-1971 (Box 5)
  - Association of Teachers of Preventative Medicine, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Commission on Reduction of Excess Hospital Capacity, 1977-1980; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Committee on Implications of Declining Pediatric Hospitalization Rates, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Committee for National Health Insurance, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Committee on Scholarly Communications with People's Republic of China, 1972-1985; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Conferences on China
    - Public Health in People's Republic of China, Ann Arbor, 1972
      - Arrangements (Box 6)
      - Correspondence (Box 6)
      - Papers submitted (Box 6)
      - Conference Report, "Public Health in the People's Republic of China", 1972-1974 (Box 6)
    - Health Care in China, Johnson Foundation, Racine Wisconsin, 1973 (Box 6)
    - China Coordination Committee, 1982 (Box 6)
  - Council on Social Work Education, 1961 (Box 6)
  - CUSP (Centro Universitario de Salud Publica) Collaboration, 1987-1990 (Box 6)
  - Federation of American Scientists, 1975-1987 (Box 6)
  - Florida International University, School of Public Health, 1981-1984 (Box 6)
  - Florida Master of Public Health, 1975-1986 (Box 6)
  - Ford Executive Committee meeting, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Governor's Action Committee on Health Care
    - Minutes, Memos, 1964-1966; 6 folders (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1965 (Box 6)
  - Health Task Force on Vietnam, 1966 (Box 7)
  - International Pediatric Congress, Hawaii, 1986 (Box 7)
  - International Symposium on Human Rights, Retardation and Research, Kennedy Foundation, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Journal of Public Health Policy, 1986-1988 (Box 7)
  - Medical Malpractice, 1983; 1984 (Box 7)
  - National Association of States Universities and Land Grant Colleges, 1967-1971 (Box 7)
  - National Immunization Conference, 1977 (Box 7)
  - National Research Council, 1975-1979
    - Board on Maternal, Child, and Family Health Research, 1977-1979; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - General, 1975-1977 (Box 7)
  - Pediatric Research Organizations, 1961-1965 (Box 7)
  - Physicians for Social Responsibility, 1985-1989 (Box 7)
  - President's Conference on Heart Disease and Cancer, 1961 (Box 7)
  - President's Science Advisory Committee on South American Problems, 1960-1961 (Box 7)
  - Project HEADSTART, 1965-1968; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Resources for the Future, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Scientific Club, 1968-1973 (Box 7)
  - Seminar on the Rational Uses of Medicine, 1974-1978; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Seminar at US Army Russian Institute, 1986 (Box 7)
  - World Health Organization (WHO), 1950-1991
    - Early Correspondence, 1950-1961 (Box 7)
    - Pan American Health Organization
      - Correspondence, 1974-1991; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Reports, 1957-1980 (Box 7)
      - Latin American Center for Educational Technology in Health (CLATES), 1982 (Box 8)
    - Pan American Health and Education Foundation, 1974-1986
      - Correspondence, 1967; 1971-1986; 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Minutes, 1975-1978; 1983; 1988-1990 (Box 8)
    - Teaching of Preventative Medicine in Medical Schools, Philippines, 1970 (Box 8)
    - Trip Files (Box 8)
    - Trip Diaries, 5 folders (Box 8)
      (including Switzerland, 1950, Cuba, 1975, South America, 1976, Brazil, 1981 and three trips to China)
    - Trip-related correspondence, 1964-1984 (Box 8)
      (scattered)
    - Trip Reports, 3 folders (Box 8)
      (Ecuador, Korea, Malaya)
- Post-Retirement Activities, 1974-1993
  The fifth series is the Post-Retirement Period, 1974-1993. Here the researcher will find extensive correspondence reflective of Wegman's numerous activities and travels primarily in a professional capacity. He was very active in the National Fellows Program funded by the Kellogg Foundation. Wegman kept this separate post-retirement correspondence file, dealing with many of his interests, particularly the University of Michigan and the World Health Organization.
  - Correspondence
    - Johns Hopkins University, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Kellogg Foundation
      - International Health proposal, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Seminars, 1984-1988 (Box 8)
      - National Fellows Program, 1982-1991; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Legislators, 1979-1984 (Box 9)
    - Social Security (Box 9)
    - General Correspondence
      - 1974-1985, 12 folders
      - 1986-1993, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - Notes, Outlines, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Reports, Speeches
    - 1977-1987 (Box 10)
    - National Academy of Sciences, Pesticide Information Review and Evaluation Committee (PIREC), 1977 (Box 10)
- Reprints, 1930-1989
  Reprints, 1930-1989 series contains publications for Wegman's entire career. A full publications list can be found in the Biographical folder in Box 1.
  - Vital Statistics Pediatrics, 1950-1982
    - Articles (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (Box 10)
  - Chronological File
    - 1930-1939 (Box 10)
    - 1940-1949 (Box 10)
    - 1950-1959, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - 1961-1969 (Box 10)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 11)
    - 1980-1985, 1989 (Box 11)
  - Book Reviews (Box 11)
  - Brennemann's Practice of Pediatrics, Chapter 7, Community Aspects of Child Health, 1972 (Box 11)
- Topical File
  Topical Files series was originally arranged in alphabetical order with classification of folders by state or country. For ease of research the folders are filed by actual topic in most cases. This series represents, for the most part, post-retirement activities, many of them continuous from before Wegman's retirement.
  - Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1964; 1975 (Box 11)
    (Pediatrics text book)
  - Audio Tapes (Box 11)
    (include lectures, celebratory occasions, conferences, etc.)
  - Australia, 1976-1978 (Box 11)
  - Brazil, 1975-1985 (Box 11)
  - California, 1974-1988 (Box 11)
  - Canada, 1975-1988 (Box 11)
  - Chile, 1975-1985 (Box 11)
  - China, 1974-1988 (Box 11)
  - Cosmos Club (Box 11)
  - Harvard University (Box 11)
  - International Science and Technology Institute, Inc., 1986-1988 (Box 11)
  - John Sparkman Center for International Public Health Education, 1979-1986 (Box 11)
  - Maryland Department of Health and Human Services, 1975-1976 (Box 11)
  - Memorials (Box 11)
  - National Center for Toxicological Research, 1975-1976 (Box 11)
  - National Sanitation Foundation (Box 11)
  - Puerto Rico (Box 11)
  - Singapore, 1983 (Box 11)
  - Tulane University, 1988 (Box 11)
  - United States-Mexico Border Public Health Association (Box 11)
  - Washington, DC, 1970-1988; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Wisconsin Residency Program in Preventative Medicine, 1966-1977; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Yale University (Box 11)